MARINA KNITTEL

 $(650) \cdot 575 \cdot 7145 \diamond mknittel@cs.umd.edu$ Iribe 5104, 8125 Paint Branch Dr, College Park, MD, 20740 Website: mknittel.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research focuses on graph algorithms for (1) scalable machine learning, (2) market and diffusion modeling, and (3) classical problems in computer science (i.e., matching, coloring, etc.). Some of my previous works include distributed and streaming edge coloring, distributed and fair hierarchical clustering, and multi-agent games of influence. I am currently working on distributed matching, partitioning methods for high-dimensional geometry, and a stable marriage model for the faculty hiring market.

EDUCATION

University of Maryland, College Park

PhD in Computer Science

MS in Computer Science, 3.97 GPA

Drof MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi and Drof John Diglargan

Advisors: Prof. MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi and Prof. John Dickerson

Coursework: Approximation Algorithms, Modern Discrete Probability, Algorithms in Machine Learning, Computational Geometry, Algorithmic Lower Bounds, Computational Linguistics, Quantum Information Theory, Computational Genomics

Harvey Mudd College

Claremont, CA

College Park, MD

Expected: May 2023

May 2018

May 2020

B.S. in Computer Science and Mathematics, 3.75 GPA

Advanced Coursework: Advanced Algorithms, Computational Complexity, Graph Theory, Convex Set Theory, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Logic, Advanced Linear Algebra

HONORS AND AWARDS

External	Google CSRMP Class of 2021 CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women	2021 2021
University of Maryland	Dean's Fellow	2018 - 2020
Harvey Mudd College	Class of '94 Award	2018
	High Distinction	2018
	Honors in Computer Science	2018
	Honors in Mathematics	2018
	Dean's List	2015 - 2018
Palo Alto High School	Sandra Forsythe Memorial Scholarship	2014

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

^{abc}Denotes that authors are listed **alphabetically**. This is convention in theoretical computer science. Computer science traditionally uses competitive conferences (15-30% accepted) as the main publication venue.

Conference:

- 1. [Submitted] ^{abc}MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi, Marina Knittel, Hamed Saleh, and Hsin-Hao Su, "Massively Parallel Constant-round Tree Contraction".
- 2. [Submitted] ^{abc}AmirMohsen Ahanchi, Alexandr Andoni, MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi, Marina Knittel, and Peilin Zhong, "Massively Parallel Tree Embeddings for High Dimensional Spaces".

- 3. [In Prep] Marina Knittel, Samuel Dooley, and John P. Dickerson, "The Binary Affiliate Matching Problem: Approval-Based Matching with Applicant-Employer Relations".
- 4. ^{abc}Fotini Christia, Michael Curry, Constantinos Daskalakis, Erik Demaine, John P. Dickerson, MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi, Adam Hesterberg, Marina Knittel, and Aidan Millif, "Scalable Equilibrium Computation in Multi-agent Influence Games on Networks". The Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2020.
- abc Sara Ahmadian, Alessandro Epasto, Marina Knittel, Ravi Kumar, Mohammad Mahdian, Benjamin Moseley, Sergei Vassilvitskii, Philip Pham, and Yuyan Wang. "Fair Hierarchical Clustering". The Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2020.
- 6. ^{abc}MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi and Marina Knittel, "Matching Affinity Clustering: Improved Hierarchical Clustering at Scale with Guarantees". The International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS), 2020. Extended abstract.
- 7. ^{abc}Soheil Behnezad, Mahsa Derakhshan, MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi, Marina Knittel, and Hamed Saleh, "Streaming and Massively Parallel Algorithms for Edge Coloring". The 27th Annual European Symposium on Algorithms (ESA), 2019.
- 8. Jordan R. Abrahams, David A. Chu, Grace Diehl, Marina Knittel, Judy Lin, William Lloyd, James C. Boerkoel Jr., and Jeremy Frank, "DREAM: An Algorithm for Mitigating the Overhead of Robust Rescheduling". The 29th International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS), 2019.
- Hoaxing Du, Yi Sheng Ong, Marina Knittel, Ross Mawhorter, Ivy Liu, Gianluca Gross, Reiko Tojo, Ran Libeskind-Hadas, and Yi-Chieh Wu, "Multiple Optimal Reconciliations with Gene Duplication, Loss, and Coalescence". The 17th Asia Pacific Bioinformatics Conference (APBC), 2019.

Presentations:

- 1. "Scalable Equilibrium Computation in Multi-agent Influence Games on Networks". AAAI-21. Full talk and short talk.
- 2. "Fair Hierarchical Clustering". NeurIPS-20. Short talk.
- 3. "Matching Affinity Clustering: Improved Hierarchical Clustering at Scale with Guarantees". AAMAS-20.
- 4. "Fair Hierarchical Clustering". The Sets & Partitions Workshop at NeurIPS-19.
- 5. "Trade-offs Between Communication, Rescheduling, and Success Rate in Uncertain Multi-Agent Schedules". IntEX Workshop at ICAPS-18.

Workshop Papers, etc.:

- 1. ^{abc}Sara Ahmadian, Alessandro Epasto, Marina Knittel, Ravi Kumar, Mohammad Mahdian, and Philip Pham. "Fair Hierarchical Clustering". The Sets & Partitions Workshop at the 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2019. Workshop; subsumed by conference submission.
- 2. ^{abc}Soheil Behnezad, Mahsa Derakhshan, MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi, Marina Knittel, and Hamed Saleh, "Edge Coloring: MPC and Streaming Algorithms". The 33rd International Symposium on Distributed Computing (DISC), 2019. Brief announcement; subsumed by ESA-19 paper.
- 3. David A. Chu, Grace Diehl, Marina Knittel, Judy Lin, Liam Lloyd, James C. Boerkoel Jr., and Jeremy Frank, "Trade-offs Between Communication, Rescheduling, and Success Rate in Uncertain Multi-Agent Schedules". The Integrated Planning, Acting and Execution Workshop (IntEx) at

The 28th International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS), 32-40, 2018. Workshop; subsumed by ICAPS-19 paper.

WORK AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Amazon May 2020 - August 2020

Research Scientist Intern

Seattle, WA

· Learned and evaluated dense embeddings of ads metadata for click-through rate prediction

· Parsed and vectorized complex boolean expressions as a part of ads metadata

Google LLC May 2019 - August 2019

Software Engineering Intern

Seattle, WA

Developed and bounding efficient algorithms for hierarchical clustering without over-representation

· Migrated and improved open sourced tools for graph regularization using Keras (TensorFlow)

May 2018 - August 2018 Facebook, Inc.

Software Engineering Intern

Menlo Park, CA

· Developed, trained, and tuned new neural network models for suggesting Instagram accounts to follow

· Incorporated handling for sparsed, crossed, and bucketized features in the training pipeline

NASA Ames & Harvey Mudd College

August 2017 - June 2018

Senior Capstone Project Manager and Member

Claremont, CA

· Led a team of 5 in a research-based project in scheduling algorithms

- Researched new methods for optimizing multi-agent system rescheduling with limited communication
- · Theoretically and experimentally verified effect of communication on success

Rutgers University

May 2017 - August 2017

REU Scholar in Theoretical Computer Science

Piscataway, New Jersey

- Summer 2017 NSF-funded REU position under Professor Eric Allender at DIMACS
- Studied the Minimum Circuit Size Problem, Kolmogorov Random Strings and the Polynomial Hierarchy
- · Modified the Turing machine to produce a hierarchy almost isomorphic to the Polynomial Hierarchy

Harvey Mudd College

August 2016 - May 2018

Researcher in Computational Biology

Claremont, CA

- · Developed a new algorithm for fast and effective reconciliation for non-binary phylogenetic trees
- · Proved various mathematical properties of a data structure used in phylogenetic reconciliation research
- Analyzed effectiveness of the binary phylogenetic tree reconciliation algorithm

Bloomberg LP May 2016 - July 2016 New York City, NY

Software Engineering Intern

· Built a service to assume a front end process and lighten client machine processing load

Gained a deeper understanding of computer systems, C++, and elegant and adaptable coding practices

Harvey Mudd College

June 2015 - May 2016

Researcher in Web Development

Claremont, California

· Improved a research websites appeal and functionality (HTML, CSS, Javascript, PHP and Drupal)

· Trained new researchers in web development and coding practices to join the web development team

May 2014 - August 2014

Santa Barbara, CA

· Programmed a blog in JavaScript (jQuery), HTML, and CSS, using Bootstrap for a start-up

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

September 2018 - December 2019

University of Maryland, College Park

College Park, MD

- · Courses: Discrete Structures, Cryptography
- · Responsibilities: Lead recitations, hold tutoring hours, grade tests

Grader and Tutor

January 2015 - May 2018

Harvey Mudd College

Harvey Mudd College

Claremont, CA

- · Courses: Algorithms, Computational Complexity, Machine Learning, Data Structures & Program Development, Introductury Computer Science, Multivariable Calculus
- · Responsibilities: Hold tutoring hours, grade homeworks

Homework Hotline Tutor

September 2014 - December 2016

Claremont, CA

· Provided free over-the-phone tutoring for K-12 students

SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP

TI A A AND I A AND I COMMON TO A COMMON AND	Now
University of Maryland LGBTQ+ Event Coordinator 2019 -	11011
CATS Theory Lecture Organizer 2019 -	Now
Executive Committee Member 2018 -	Now
CS Women Mentor 2018 -	2020
Graduate Admissions Volunteer 2018 -	2019
Harvey Mudd College Committee for Activities Planning Member 2017 -	2018
Women in Math Club President 2017 -	2018
LGBTQ+ Club Mentor 2017 -	2018
Dorm President 2016 -	2017
Dorm Treasurer 2015 -	2016